Welcome everyone to CS 33336
language models from scratch. Um, this
is a teaching staff. I'm Percy, this is
Tatsu, Marcel, Herman, and Steven, and
we're bringing you the third edition of
336. So, we'll just do a quick round of
introductions. Um, so I'd like to say
that I've been doing language models for
20 years, but most of that time was uh
of small language models. Um, actually
this is still small in the grand scheme
of things. Um,
I think when Tatsu and I started
teaching this class uh 2 years ago, we
weren't really sure of what we were
going to expect, but we were very
pleasantly surprised that so many people
wanted to learn how to build language
models from scratch, especially in these
days when a coding agent could probably
zero-shot a language model. Um, I'm
really glad to see all of you here to
actually want to learn how they work.
Yeah, thanks. Uh, I'm Tatsu. I'm one of
the co-instructors. I'll be, you know,
talking to you once we get to
architectures and scaling and all these
other very fun things. Um, I'm really
excited. This is the the most fun class
I've taught in my time here. Um, I think
every year, you know, Percy makes fun of
me because he says you have to redo all
your lectures because you took on
architectures and everything changes
every time. Um, but it's actually pretty
fun for me to do it and it's kind of the
first time that I've had that
experience. So, I'm looking forward to
uh going through this experience again
with you all.
Hello, I'm Marcel. Uh, I've seen this
class once before and I'm I'm returning
cuz it was so much fun last time.
Uh,
uh it's it's a lot of work though. Um,
in my research I do architecture stuff.
I do higher-order gradients and I do
training. Um, yeah, looking forward to
work with you guys.
Hello everyone, I'm Herman. Uh, a year
ago I didn't really know how LLMs
worked. So, I think for me tokens were
the things you collect in video games
and attention was the thing you had like
the attention economy.
Um, then after spending a lot of time on
this course last year, I'm now doing uh
LLM research and I'm really excited to
TA this year.
Hi everyone, I'm Steven. I am a
first-time CA for this course and I'm
very excited about it. I think it'll be
a lot of fun. Broadly in my research I
work on language models, theory, and
some data efficiency stuff and I'm
excited to meet you all.
All right, so let's let's go into
things.
Um,
so this is the third time we're offering
it.
Um, last year we decided to put all our
lectures on YouTube, so some of you will
have seen it. Um, so what's new? Um,
well, what hasn't changed is the from
scratch philosophy. We still believe
strongly that by building everything
from the ground up, you really learn
um
how everything works.
Um, of course, we don't actually build
everything up from from scratch because
that would be, you know, that wouldn't
fit in a quarter.
Um, so over the the last 2 years we've
been refining our our recipe and
figuring out what are the things that
you build up from scratch that are most
highly value. And then finally, as Tatsu
alluded to, um even in a year
a lot has changed. Um, I think um this
year we're
we're going to spend maybe a bit more
time on mixture of experts and of course
agents are very uh
um popular these days, so getting uh a
handle on long context and what is
needed for that are going to be
important.
So, why do we make this this course? And
I think the problem through uh 2 years
ago was
that researchers were becoming
disconnected from the underlying
technology. Used to be the case um
maybe 10 years ago, all AI researchers
would just implement and train their own
models.
And then even 8 years ago,
um people would download uh pre-trained
models such as uh BERT and fine-tune
them. And I think a lot of today
um you can get by by simply prompting a
model.
And of course, there's nothing wrong
with prompting a model. You know, I
think you can do really amazing things
with it. Um, I think moving up the
abstraction in general is is a great
thing, but abstractions are leaky and
sometimes if if I'm sure all of you have
prompted models, you run into situations
where something is you wanted to do
something, but you it just can't do it
and there's no recourse. Um,
and I would argue that if you're really
interested in fundamental uh research,
uh by simply prompting a model, you're
sort of vastly constraining the set of
options, the design space you're looking
at. And by uh looking at fundamental
research, you really need to tear up the
whole stack.
So, I would argue that full
understanding of how language models
work is really necessary for fundamental
research. And the way that we're going
to get our understanding is by building.
That's the philosophy of the class.
But there's one small problem, which is
that industrialization of language
models has happened. Frontier models are
really really expensive. Even this is 3
years ago, uh GPT-4 was supposedly
costing 100 um million dollars to train
and now costs probably are on the order
of you know, a billion, although that's
uh speculative. And the number of GPUs
that um all the big labs are building is
just kind of immense. Furthermore,
there's no details on how many of these
models are built. So, even back in uh
2023, the GPT-4 paper explicitly says
that due to competitive landscape and
safety implications, we're not going to
share anything about how the models are
being built.
So, these frontier models are in some
sense out of the reach for us. Now, we
could build small language models and we
will build small language models, but
this I think it's important to remember
that these might not representative of
um the actual frontier models. And I'll
give you two examples why uh this is
might be the case.
So, here's one.
Of course, this is from actually quite a
long time ago. Um, think back in 2021.
If uh we're going to spend more time on
flop counting and looking at where the
computer is being spent, but if you look
at small scales, the a fraction of flops
spent in uh the MLP layers is around 44%
and if you scale up to 175B,
then it goes to 80, you know, percent.
So, what you optimize and what matters
at large scale is going to be different
from small scale. So, if you did a bunch
of small scale stuff here um on the
attention, you might not experience the
same benefits at large scale.
Um, the second I example is that we know
of emergence um of behavior with scale.
So, small models um this is again for a
while ago, but even back then, um if you
uh have um
zero-shot or few-shot learning of
various tasks, it basically seemed like
nothing was working. And only when you
reach a critical scale, do you suddenly
see a lot of improvement. So, again, if
you're working at small scale, you might
not see certain types of phenomenon
compared to if you were working at full
scale.
Okay, so that might be a little bit uh
disheartening, uh but fear not, we're
going to learn something in this class.
And the question is what can we learn
that actually transfers?
Okay, and I think it's important to
break this down into three types of
knowledge.
First,
there's the mechanics of how things
work, what a transformer is, how model
parallelism works, right? Um, there's
mindset, which is how do you go about
approaching building a language model.
Um, we're going to talk about how you
want to squeeze the most out of your
hardware, taking scaling seriously.
And in finally, intuitions, which data
modeling decisions are going to yield
good uh performance.
So, now in this class, I think we can do
a pretty good job of teaching the
mechanics, uh which is how things work,
and the mindset. And we're going to
really emphasize that you profile and
benchmark everything and try to optimize
for efficiency.
These things do transfer to a larger
scale.
Now, the intuitions about what modeling
decisions and what um data decisions
do work uh might not necessarily
transfer across scales. Um, for that you
actually have to go somewhere where you
can have do things at scale.
So, on the note of intuitions,
um
it is worth remarking re- uh remarking
that some design decisions are just not
justifiable. Um,
and just purely come from
experimentation. Whereas mechanics, you
can kind of by construction see how uh
the parallelism and how kernels are
going to speed things up and so on. Um,
but for intuitions about what modeling
changes work, um I think you just have
to run experiments. There's this famous
Noam Shazeer paper that introduces the
SwiGLU activation, which we're going to
look about. And in the conclusion
section, um he very honestly has this
final uh
sentence which says, "We offer no
explanation. We attribute their success
of these architectures all else to
divine benevolence." So, um that in some
sense is something that you just have to
gain from
experience.
Final note about the the bitter lesson,
which I think has been um been, you
know, circulating and people talk about
it. I think there's a sort of a common
mis-
conception here what it means. I think
the wrong interpretation is that scale
is all that matters, algorithms don't
matter.
But that's not correct. The right
interpretation is that algorithms that
scale are what that or what matters.
Okay? And you can think about very
simply that the accuracy of your model
is basically your efficiency
times
uh the resources. So, efficiency is
output over input and resources is the
input. Um,
and
you know, efficiency is is actually in
some sense way more important at
larger scale, right? If you're doing a
small scale experiment, if your run
takes twice as long, maybe you just wait
twice as long and and then
you come back later. But if you're doing
things at scale, you know, that could
be, you know, hundreds of millions of
dollars and you know, definitely don't
want to do that. Even like a 5%
improvement might be a big deal.
So in fact, efficiency is actually
really really critical and I hope to
bake that into your your kind of mindset
as one of the consequences of this
class.
And empirically, if you look at there's
this paper from
OpenAI in 2020 that showed there's a 44x
algorithmic efficiency on ImageNet
between 2012 and 2019.
And it's surely the case that hardware
did get a lot better. Um but that also
comes with algorithmic improvements and
of course, when you multiply them
together, that's when you see like a
huge bump in
um in efficiency and
accuracy.
So the framing um
with all of that said is what is the
best model one can build with a certain
data and compute budget?
Um for pre-training, it's mostly we're
going to talk about compute budget
because we're going to try assume that
we have a lot of more data than we have
compute, but if you're in
a setting where you're data limited or
you have
you know, stash away actually tons of
B200s, then you might be
uh
data bound.
So in other words, maximize efficiency
and we're going to see this theme come
up throughout the class.
Okay. So so next I want to spend a bit
of time talking about language models
and a bit of a history and just
contextualization before we jump into
the more technical details.
Um so language models have been around
for a while. Um
you know, Shannon back in the 50s was
using language models to measure the
entropy of English. Um and for a long
time, N-gram models
were used actually in machine
translation and speech recognition
systems. Um
and they weren't the whole system, but
they were important part of making sure
that you generated fluid text.
Um I would say that the the lineage of
the modern language models comes from
neural architectures.
And so there is a bunch of
uh ideas, I think, which are important
to this development. So
in the 90s, there was LSTMs.
Joshua Bengio actually
you know, wrote the first neural
language model in paper back in 2003.
This was actually not LSTM. This was
just a feedforward network that looked
at the small context. Um and then there
was a seek-to-seek modeling which
boldly said we can actually compress a
whole sentence into a a vector. Um the
Adam optimizer, attention mechanism
which was developed for machine
translation, the transformer
architecture which built on top of that
which was also developed for machine
translation. And then scaling up to
mixture of experts,
uh model parallelism, you see a lot of
different architecture and also systems
and optimizer ideas
in developing the 2010s.
And then by the late 2010s, I think
things were starting to get really
interesting. So
there was the ELMo and BERT. These are
language models that
were trained on lots of text and then
they you could fine-tune them on some
downstream tasks like question answering
and it would show a huge improvement on
that. So the the model there was, you
know, take one of these models and then
fine-tune.
Um and then Google
had a paper that was really I think
foreshadowing this view of, you know,
prompt in response out.
So it was really I think OpenAI that
really
opened up the floodgates here by
embracing scaling. So they had a GPT
paper back in I think 2018 or so that
they scaled up to GPT-2 and then
and then they
really figured out
you know, or embraced the idea of
scaling laws
which we're going to talk about in a in
a second
which enabled them to train GPT-3
which was a much more massive, almost
more than 10x larger large model at the
time. And it could show emergent
behavior like in-context learning.
At that point,
you know, Google was saying, "Okay, we
need to do something too." So they
trained a massive model. It turned out
to be kind of under-trained
and turned out that their DeepMind which
was not integrated with Google at the
time had you know, figured out you know,
optimal compute optimal scaling laws.
Um so all this was was happening and
after GPT-3 came out, I think for a many
folks, this was sort of kind of wake-up
call.
And at that time, there were a lot of
early attempts to let's try to replicate
this.
So there was a grassroots organization
called Luther that created some open
data sets and models. They weren't very
large because they didn't have
much compute. Meta's uh first LLM was uh
you know, it was you could see tell that
it's a replication because it was like
175 billion parameters.
Um but it was not a very good model.
Um they ran into a lot of hardware
issues.
Um
and then there was another Hugging Face
Big Science project. So these models
were I would say not a very strong.
Then in the last 3 years, I think the
open model ecosystem has changed quite a
bit with Meta kind of leading the way
with the Llama series of models, Llama,
Llama 2, Llama 3. Mistral got in the
game. And then a whole set of Chinese
um
models uh um I I think I'm missing some
like ByteDance has something and
um I think Tencent probably has some
other stuff. So it's hard to keep track
of everything, but you know, everyone's
heard of Deep Seek and Qwen.
Um so I think I got the the
um main ones. But I think what's
interesting and exciting about these is
now now we have open weight models that
are approaching closed models. So
depending on who you are asking and how
you benchmark, they might be a little
bit behind or comparable, but they are
definitely very very credible models
that are being widely used in
industry.
Now there's an another line of work
which is going beyond just releasing
open weight models.
AI2, Nvidia, and
the Marine project which I work on,
we try to
provide not just the weights, but the
paper and the code and the data so that
we can understand how these models are
built
in a more thorough way.
Why do I emphasize this open ecosystem
so much?
Mostly because this course would not be
possible I think without these models.
By the fact that there are still many
papers that are being published about
how these big MOEs and RL systems are
working
enables us to at least glimpse into how
these frontier models are being built
and trying to triangulate the pieces.
Now I think of course a lot of the
details even with these like you know,
Qwen papers, I think they're missing a
lot of details. You can't reproduce
them. Notably the data mixture is is
something that we don't know, but I
think it's better much better than
nothing.
Okay. So
in the last
decade, I think the idea of what a
language model has changed. Right? It
used to be something that you you
fine-tune.
Um and then it was something you prompt.
And now in the ChatGPT era, it was
something you talk to and that you can
have a you know, conversation with. And
now
okay, I guess I don't have internet. Um
that's fine.
Um
and now we're in the era of agents. If
you click on this link, it basically
shows you a giant agent trace.
Um and I'm I'm still kind of it's
mind-boggling how
um
strong some of these models are. You
give it like a page of text and it does
have some really complicated agentic
coding task.
Um so you know, what we demand of our
language models today is probably beyond
the imagination of anyone back you know,
10 years ago.
That said, I think the fundamentals I
think haven't changed that much.
Largely, we still build on GPUs and
kernels. We still optimize using
gradient or stochastic gradient like
approaches. We still have the
transformer and attention and you know,
we'll we'll talk a little bit more about
architectures, but it hasn't changed
that much. I think the specs are
different. Now we demand greater context
lengths which means that inference
efficiency matters even more.
So the good news for us is that we
didn't have to completely change this
class,
only touch two sections on the latest
you know, Chinese architectures, but
the the fundamentals I think are here to
stay at least for now.
Okay. Maybe I'll pause there in case
there's any questions or or thoughts.
Okay. So let's let's go on. So brief
interlude.
So what is this program?
Um so this is what I call an executable
lecture. This is a if if you think it
looks like a Python program, it is
because it is actually a Python program,
um but it has been rendered for your
viewing pleasure. Um so when I step
through it, it is actually executing the
the lecture and it makes us it possible
to basically step through code and which
will be hopefully interesting and
important later. And you can also see
the hierarchical structure of this
lecture. For example, we're done with
this function now we go back to main.
Okay, so let's talk about the course
logistics
and the syllabus which I think it's
going to take the
good chunk of time.
Okay, so all the information is online
on this website or cs336.stanford.edu.
This is a five unit class.
I think this probably class has a
certain reputation so I don't need to
belabor the point too much but you know,
this is
we have five assignments. They are
pretty intense even the first assignment
according to this one
um
review was actually you know, equivalent
to the five assignments for cs224n. I've
been told also this is like wait this is
exaggerated um but better to I guess be
conservative in your estimates. So
why should you so why should you take
this course? Okay, so first you have an
obsessive need like me to understand how
things work. That should be your primary
objective. I think just pure curiosity
on how language models work and then in
doing the class you'll develop a much
stronger research you know, engineering
muscles and have the confidence to go
into a new setting and
be
equipped to deal with whatever comes up.
So
I think when I started at Stanford I
screwed this class called you know,
statistical learning theory which was
basically teaching the theoretical side
of machine learning and that was nice
because it equipped people so when you
read a paper you can understand all the
math and now since the field has kind of
shifted a lot more towards this more
systems and empirical side of things.
This is sort of the
kind of an analogous class which gives
people enough depth that they feel
that everything else seems
kind of easy.
So why should you not take this course?
This is important because there's
reasons you shouldn't take this course.
First you actually want to get some
research done this quarter.
You should probably talk to your
advisor. They should know you're taking
this course otherwise they'll be
probably
there might be some surprises. You're
interested in learning the hottest new
techniques in AI.
I think there are many other great
courses
you know, seminar courses topics courses
that are good for that. We don't do all
many of the things we don't do
multi-modality. We don't talk
about you know, agents in any depth. So
if you want to learn about this that
stuff this is not the right course for
that.
If you come in and say like I have an
application domain I want to
get good results on it.
Probably this is not the right course at
least to start.
I always recommend just prompt the model
fine tune the model and then as a last
resort you pre-train your own model
because it is a pain and it's also
expensive. But it's a lot of fun.
Okay, so if you're
not taking the class you can soft follow
along at home. So all the lecture
materials will be posted on the website
oops and
they are also recorded through cgoe so
thank you cgoe for doing that and later
they will be published to YouTube.
Um
Now of course following at home watching
the lectures is great but you learn
really by doing the assignments so
you'll have to figure out how to
motivate yourself to do that.
Okay, so speaking of assignments we have
five assignments.
The philosophy of the assignment is you
know, how how do we do the from scratch
but not just you know, say build a
language model and that's the
assignment. So we don't provide
scaffolding code but we do provide a
bunch of unit tests to make sure that
whatever you're building is actually
correct so that it's you don't get the
sparse rewards setting where you submit
a homework and it's either correct or
not.
Um
What I recommend is that
you can the assignments are structured
so that much of the assignment can
actually be done locally on your laptop.
You can implement it and check for
correctness and then we are providing a
cluster so that you can
do an actual training run to see what
the accuracy is or get a bunch of GPUs
to actually benchmark the you know,
performance of a some kernel.
Um
And then for fun we will have
you know, some leaderboards for most of
the assignments at least and they will
look something like well, now that
you've learned about this topic try to
minimize the perplexities given some
sort of budget. And and both Marcel and
Herman were masters of leaderboarding
back in the day which was last year
or the year before. So if you want tips
on that I'm sure they would be happy.
Actually I don't know if they would tell
you their secrets but
you can try.
Okay, so um
You know, last year we were thinking
about well, what can
AI do is like okay, well, I mean yes
everyone can use AI but um uh
but but you know, just try to do your
best. I think now I think coding agents
have gotten so good that they can just
also solve all the assignments, right?
But to state the obvious obviously
you're not going to learn anything if
you just feed in the PDF assignment one
into Claude code.
At the same time AI can be very useful
for answering questions and tutoring. So
we have to find a way to
you know, uh
leverage AI. So what we've decided to do
is we provide you
agents.md file or of equivalently a
prompt which asks the AI to be
pedagogically minded. You can read more
about in our AI policy guide and the
requirement is that if you're going to
use AI use it with this prompt. And so
it will answer questions about code. It
will clarify any understanding but it
won't accidentally generate like the
transformer for you when the homework is
to implement the transformer.
Okay, and this is the first year we're
trying to do this so please try it out
and give us feedback if it's working or
not working.
Okay, so compute. So this year we have
thanks to modal.
They have provided us with a compute
credits on their platform.
It's actually quite quite nice. You can
get a number of unlike last year well, I
guess
you guys didn't take the class last
year. Last year we had a cluster you SSH
into. This is using more of an API to
which I was initially skeptical of but
you know, looking at it actually is
pretty pleasant to use. So again
try it out and give us feedback on how
it is. We've written a guide on how to
access and use the compute.
Okay.
Any questions about course logistics?
All right, let's talk about what we're
going to cover in this this class.
So
um there's basically five parts
mirroring the five assignments that
you'll have. Basic systems scaling laws
data and alignment. So I'm going to now
go through each
um uh part and just give you a taste of
what you will will learn.
Okay, so
in the basics this is basically the
first um two weeks. The goal is to just
be able to train a language model and
build it from scratch. So the components
here are we're going to tokenize the
data. We're going to define architecture
and then we're going to implement
optimizer and trainer. Okay.
So then you wonder like what are the
other the rest of the class is for?
Well, we'll get to there.
So let's start with tokenization. The
tokenization is really about what are
the atoms that the model operates on.
And
you know, formally a tokenizer converts
between raw inputs which are just bytes
and a sequence of integers
which are represent the tokens.
Conceptually it's a segmentation of the
of the text. We're going to talk about
the byte pair encoding BPE tokenizer
which intuitively
breaks the input into frequently
occurring chunks.
And then remember this class is about
maximizing efficiency.
So through an efficiency lens
tokenization is good because it takes a
long sequence if you just think about
the raw byte stream and reduces it into
a smaller number of tokens.
But more subtly but maybe more
importantly it allows you to do adaptive
computation. So some
maybe some places are actually a lot of
bytes but actually it should be
compressed into a one token where some
of the
more rare or interesting parts of input
should be left as multiple tokens.
Okay, we'll talk more about this.
I just want to mention that
you know, every year I'm hoping that I
don't have to talk teach tokenization
because the dream is to really have an
end-to-end way of that directly operates
on bytes.
And there's been a number of work
including you know, recently there's
been this
this
H net work that seems promising but so
far these have not been scaled to the
frontier and since the frontier models
are still using tokenizers Uh, felt like
it would be still wise to teach
tokenizers.
Okay, so, um,
now after you tokenize your input, you
have a bunch of tokens. Now you define a
model on top, and everyone I think has a
familiarity with the rich uh the
transformer.
Um, and if you take in 224N, uh the NLP
class, then you've seen transformers.
Um,
since then, I think there have been a
lot of improvements or refinements to
transformers, which um I I think are
important, and Tatsus is going to talk
more about this in a bit. But just to
run through a set of
types of things that one might have to
think about. So, the activation
functions have uh evolved. Um,
um how do you positional encodings has
evolved? Um, how you normalize
um
um has uh the different layers to prefer
uh blow up has evolved. Um, you know,
instead of doing full attention, there's
many uh ways to basically reduce the
attention computation because attention
is n squared and it's and where n is a
sequence length and that gets really
expensive.
Um, so there's a bunch of ideas around
that. Uh, if you're more ambitious, uh
you can look at these uh state space
models or you know equivalently uh
linear attention. Um,
like Mamba and gated DeltaNet. These
have become been popular in the last uh
you know few years, and usually some
hybrid between these models and
attention seems to work uh you know
quite well. So, we'll be exploring some
of that.
Um, and then within the MLP layers of
the transformer, um the original
transformer was just a dense um MLP, and
now mixture of experts um has become the
sort of a dominant paradigm for building
compute efficient um your transformer.
So, we're going to talk about um that.
And of course with M MLP a mixture of
experts,
you know, it's not just defining your
architecture, but we'll see that we'll
also need uh different uh techniques for
training um the model.
And then finally, perhaps somewhat
boringly, but an important uh question
is, you know, what is the shape of your
transformer? How many layers? Uh how
many heads? Um what is hidden dimension?
Number of experts?
Um this might come in more as we talk
about scaling laws, but setting these um
is actually seems kind of
you know, almost trivial. It's a
hyperparameter, but actually in the
context of uh scaling um language models
has a huge huge uh um implication.
Okay. So, once you define your model
architecture, um how do you train the
model?
Um, and here there's a bunch of design
decisions around the loss function.
There's next word next token prediction,
which is the default, um but people have
found that um looking at predicting more
than one token seems to uh be helpful
for improving the model. Um,
and
um there's optimizers. People used to
use um Adam, but increasingly Muon has
been used especially with some of the
latest open models such as
um
the the Kimmy K2 models. Um,
initialization,
um which is again sounds kind of you
know boring, but turns out to have a
huge impact on how um your ability in
the training stability of larger models,
learning rates uh schedule, uh
regularization,
um you know, batch size.
Um, and then MoE specific things.
So, you know, you look at this list and
you might think, well, these are just
hyperparameters. I'm going to try a
bunch of um different options out. But
it turns out that, you know, really
being very careful of about uh setting
these hyperparameters in a principled
way will make the difference between a
run that just blows up and is useless
between a run that is achieving state of
the art.
Okay. I'll come back to that point when
we talk about scaling laws. Okay, so
then in assignment one, what you're
going to do is you're going to implement
the BPE tokenizer,
um implement the transformer, the loss
function, optimizer, the whole training
stack. We're going to make you do a
bunch of resource accounting, so you
understand where your flops are uh are
going. You're going to train some models
on uh these beta sets like tiny stories
and open web uh text. And then there's
going to be a leaderboard um
that where you're going to try to drive
down perplexity as uh as fast as you
can. So, uh for those of you familiar
with the NanoGPT speedruns, it's kind of
uh similar to that.
>> [clears throat]
>> Okay. So, by the end of assignment one,
you should be able to walk away and
build a language model uh you know, from
scratch.
So, that's very exciting. The you know,
if you have a if I have a high-level uh
takeaway here, it's that
you know, while the tokenizer and
modeling and training are sort of
presented as distinct pieces, it is
actually you know, everything is about
kind of balancing the the following. So,
you want expressive models because you
want to represent the complexities of
the data, but at the same time,
you want to um your training to be
stable. And we're going to see uh talk a
lot about um
how do you keep the parameter and um
gradient norms in the sort of Goldilocks
zone, so they don't blow up and they
don't vanish. Turns out a lot of
training language models is about just
you know, stab a stability. Um, and then
finally efficiency, which is um somewhat
more straightforward. You just make it
run fast on hardware. But you're going
to see interesting things like, you
know, if we change the architecture, a
lot of the architecture decisions are,
well, we can make it faster by let's say
reducing
the um the projecting our low
dimensional space. But then the question
is, does it work as well? And so, um
making those tradeoffs is something that
uh
is going to is sort of the name of the
the game here.
Okay, so,
um as in assignment two, we're going to
dive more deeply into um you know,
systems.
Um, and the goal here is just to get
most out of your hardware. Uh, so we're
going to talk about kernels, how you
parallelize across multiple GPUs, and
and how you do inference.
So,
um the basics, which we're actually
going to start on our next lecture. Um,
I mentioned resource accounting, and I
think you know, you've all probably you
know, built models
um but this is really about kind of um
keeping track of all where all the flops
go. And where all the memory is being
spent. So, we're going to spend some
time basically doing the resource
accounting. Um, we're going to see, you
know, um this this formula that comes
up, how do you how many flops does
training a 7B on model on 1 trillion
tokens? Well, it's 6 * n * d roughly.
Um, and where does that come from?
Um, and then we're going to look at
um you know, the hardware. And here's a
very cartoon I'd
you know, picture of what
what to remark about hardware is that
your memory is not where your compute
is, and you have to move uh your either
your parameters or activations into uh
from the memory to compute, do the
compute, and move it back. Right? And
that often is the bottleneck. Um,
so, you know, for example, a B200s,
which we'll have the opportunity to play
with, um
has uh 2.25 uh petaflops per second if
uh BF16, and has uh 8 terabytes um
a second of memory. So, you know, what
does that mean? I think in when we I
think I'll do this uh next lecture.
We're going to break this down and use
this information to do some um
calculations and see how long uh
different types of algorithms will need
to take.
We're going to talk about roofline
analysis, which allows us to understand
whether um a computation is bottlenecked
by either compute or memory. In general,
it it is um
um you know, memory.
Uh, and then talk a little bit about
benchmarking and profiling.
Okay, so, um
so here's what uh
uh you know, DGX B200 looks like. You
have eight GPUs. Um, they're connected
via you know, NV
link.
Um, and then if you have
many if you have a a thousand GPUs, then
you would have multiple of these, and
they're you know, connected either
InfiniBand or Ethernet. So, uh the next
two parts when we talk about system is,
you know, kernels. So, kernel is
basically a function that runs on the
GPU, and when you're just using plain
PyTorch, you know, the
all the PyTorch primitives actually
correspond to launching particular
kernels, which are built in.
Um, so you're already using kernels uh
this you know, uh whether you know it or
not. Um, but the point is that um
if for certain types of computation, if
you look at it, you can actually write
custom kernels to make the GPUs go
faster. And the main principle here is
um organizing the compute to minimize
data movement. So, remember this
picture,
um moving
data from uh from memory is expensive,
so you want to try to minimize that. So,
just as a kind of a simple example,
suppose you wanted to compute A and B.
So, often you would have to read from
your um high bandwidth memory HBM,
compute it, write it back, and then read
again, compute it, uh write it back.
Right? So, then you're basically sending
the data back and forth twice, and uh
there's this idea called fusion where
you read it once, do both of the
computations and you write it back. And
that will
save you a lot of
time.
So, that's operator fusion. Tiling is is
kind of a more sophisticated variant
around the same idea.
There's also
GPUs have also gotten a lot more
complicated
and I'm not sure how many of these
details we'll have time to get into, but
at least we want to expose you to some
of the sort of the peculiarities, I
would say, of GPUs and the and give you
appreciation for the types of things
that one has to consider in order to
squeeze as much juice out of them as
possible.
And we'll write some kernels in and and
try.
So, what happens if you have thousands
of GPUs?
Um
So, the principle of minimize data
movement is still, you know, the same.
The only thing is that
moving data between
different GPUs is even more expensive.
We're going to talk about how these very
classic collective operations like
gather and reduce and all reduce are the
way to kind of think about
um
basically distributed, you know,
training.
The general game is that we have these
model parameters, we have activations,
gradients and optimizer states, and they
need to be sharded or split across
multiple GPUs, and of course, you need
to bring the right data to the right
nodes to make the compute and write it
back. So, there's a whole kind of
orchestration that
and how to do that efficiently is going
to be the topic of this
this unit.
And there's multiple ways to to shard.
You can shard by, you know, splitting up
your data, splitting up your model,
splitting up different layers in the
model, splitting up the sequences,
splitting up between experts, and we'll
talk about the tradeoffs that come with
each of these.
Okay, and then finally, we're going to
talk about inference, um
which, as I mentioned, is growing in
importance.
So, the goal of inference is to actually
use the model. So, you know, minor
detail here.
Um
So, inference is Of course, you need to
use inference when you're chatting with
the model, but it also is useful for
reinforcement learning.
It's useful for
for doing the rollouts, test time
compute, generating synthetic data,
evaluation. So, inference is a very
critical part of
what it means to you know, do language
modeling
work. So, um
we're probably not going to spend as
much time as I like on this because the
course is already kind of filled up, but
we'll see what we can do.
Um there was
some discussion around whether we would
should make you write inference from
scratch, but
we'll we'll see.
Um
So, the way to think about inference is
that there's two phases, a prefill and a
decode. In the prefill, you take the
prompt and then you feed all the tokens
forward and build
key value pairs. This is very much like
what happens in training. Um and then
then the decoding part, tokens are
generated one at a time. And this is the
part that is becomes
quickly memory bound, and this is why
inference is
hard, and
um so, there's many things you can do to
speed up inference. You can try to use a
cheaper model by pruning a larger model.
You can quantize, you can distill. Um
you can use this technique called
speculative decoding where you use a
cheaper model to sort of run ahead and
guess a bunch of tokens, and now you use
the full model, which can operate on
those tokens in parallel to
to see if it's good. And if you got
lucky, then you can accept all those
tokens and you're you're much faster
than if you're doing one token at a
time.
And of course, you can do systems
optimizations. There's bunch of kernels
that are designed specifically for
inference. And then one of the
interesting stuff things about inference
is that if you're running a service, you
know, queries are coming at you
at potentially different times.
Um and then you have to figure out how
to batch them up. Whereas in training,
you basically are already defining your
batches and everything is much more
predictable.
So, in assignment two,
uh there's going to be implementing
kernels um in Triton. Um and doing some
sort of parallel training. Um the
details here might actually change as
um
you know, the CAs have grand plans of um
revamping the systems. So, the the
the assignment might look a bit
different from last year's,
but it will be cover the roughly the
same material.
Um one thing I will mention is that
there's this wonderful book out of some
Google people called how to scale your
model.
And I think it's it's really nice for
providing a conceptual understanding of
like roofline analysis and transformer
math and doing
LMs conceptually. So, I highly recommend
you take a look at that. Now, the only
thing is that it's from Google, so it's
about
TPUs, but a lot of the high level
concepts are are
similar. And now they have a new chapter
on how to think about GPUs.
Okay. So,
uh
So, the third assignment is about
scaling laws. So, by now, you've trained
a language model, you can make it go
really fast
by optimizing kernels in parallel. Now,
you want to scale up.
So, how do you scale up?
So, imagine the following setting. If
you had 1e25 flops,
so this is tens of millions of dollars
of compute,
um
what what model would you train?
Okay, so this is, you know, I think a
kind of a daunting task because if you
mess up, well, that's a lot of money
down the drain.
So,
and you can't do your probably typical
hyperparameter tuning at that scale
because you only get to train one model.
And so, this is like the key problem
that you have to deal with in in
language model large language model
training that you don't have to really
deal with if you're just fine-tuning a
model or doing small scale stuff.
And so, the key conceptual shift here is
that we shouldn't think about a single
model that we're training, but really
think about a scaling recipe. And a
scaling recipe is a mapping from a flop
budget, let's say 1e25 or 1e24, to a set
of hyperparameters, basically a config
file.
And for a given scaling recipe,
what we will do is
um
run a bunch of experiments to compute
the loss that you get at smaller scales,
and then you fit a scaling law, and that
enables you to predict the loss
at a target scale. So, maybe you run
some small experiments, you fit the
scaling
the scaling law, and then you project
out what you're going to get at larger
scale.
Okay, so that's the primitive. Now,
using this, what you can do is now you
can optimize the target res the scaling
recipe targeting a larger scale using
smaller scale experiments, which is
wonderful.
And second of all, you can predict the
loss that you're going to
in theory achieve before actually
running the experiment.
Which go goes
allows you to go, you know, raise money
and you say, "Well, look, I ran the
small scale experiments and I think I
can get a really like a GPT-5 level
model. Please give me a lot of money so
I can train that model."
So,
um
one thing I think
is a maybe another
misconception is that scaling laws are
not laws of laws of nature. They don't
just happen automatically. You kind of
have to will them into existence. And
this is happens by careful construction
of a scaling recipe.
Right? And a scaling recipe, remember,
it has to extrapolate. So, what this
typically means is that you have a
sequence of hyperparameters, which say
as the scale increases, maybe the
learning rate is a constant, maybe it
drops, maybe the the batch size
increases by how much. And these are
things that a scaling recipe has to
figure out. Um
and so, you parameterize So, then,
in order to get these predictable
scaling laws, one thing that you
actually have to think about is how do
you parameterize the model in a way to
get what's called hyperparameter
transfer. Right? Meaning that this
hyperparameter you use at small scale
are either the ones that you use at
larger scale or are predictable
functions of that. Right? Because if
every scale, your learning rate acts
like sometimes 1e-5 and sometimes 1e-4,
then you're not going to be able to
magically guess the right learning rate
when you
at larger scale.
So, one shift in thinking is that the
predictability is actually at least as
important as optimality. So, you think
normally think of oh, we're trying to
optimize for, you know, efficiency here
and we want to, you know, hyperparameter
tune and and make things optimal. And
and yes, you do want to do that, but you
also want this predictability so that
you don't get at larger scale.
Okay, so that's this is kind of a stage
setting.
Um the actual scaling laws we're going
to look at are fairly
you know,
classic. So, these are
you know, some of you have might have
seen this idea of well, if you give you
a flops budget,
should you train
how should you balance training a larger
model versus training on more tokens?
And this is where the classic computer
optimal scaling laws from Kaplan et al.
and the Chinchilla so-called Chinchilla
scaling laws comes in.
The basic idea is that
you uh for each uh
flops budget, so let's say 6e18 all the
way to
uh 3e21, you uh
sweep across different um
you know uh
model sizes um and you choose the best
one. So, think about minimizing each of
these. And then you fit a curve that
allows you to uh basically predict the
number of parameters given a flops
budget.
And if you're lucky, it will lie on a
roughly on a line.
And if you're unlucky, it's going to be
all over the place, which means that you
should have no confidence that you're
going to be able to uh predict reliably.
And um
So, you know, the upshot of this is um
this is quite crude, but you know,
uh a rule of thumb is
the
um 20 times the number of parameters is
the number of data points you should uh
train on. So, a 70B parameter model
should be trained on roughly 1.4
trillion um tokens. Of course, depending
on the data set and architecture, this
number will actually vary.
Okay. Also, this doesn't take you into
account um the inference cost.
Um a lot of models these days are small,
but they're trained on way more tokens
than is computer optimal because you
want a smaller model for inference
reasons.
Okay. So, uh one fun thing that we've
been doing in uh the Moraine project is
pre-registering our results. So, we fit
a bunch of scaling um you know, uh plots
at different compute budgets. We fit a
scaling law, and we basically made these
uh predictions out to 1e22 flops. Uh
this one is actually training. If you go
to the Moraine site, you can follow
along. Um it should actually be done
maybe as earliest tonight. So, maybe on
Wednesday I'll I'll report back on how
we did and see how we manage uh register
the um
how we match the pre-registered loss.
So, the idea here is that we made a
prediction on if we were to train this
large model, which we've never trained
before, if we can predict how well it's
going to do, then that's that's really
uh nice.
Okay.
So, in assignment three,
I think I think this is a kind of a
either fun or um you know, s-
Actually, it's a fun ass- let's just say
it's a fun assignment. Um
So, we're going to define this training
API,
um which basically you give us hyper
parameters, and we're going to give you
a loss back.
So, what we're going to try to do is
simulate what happens if you could do a
lot of training runs. And of course, we
don't have enough compute to actually
allow everyone um to train their own,
you know, 8B model or anything.
So, basically, we train a bunch of
models offline, and we basically provide
this cache. Um so, it looks like you're
training.
Um and what you're going to do is submit
training jobs.
Um you give us a config. Basically, we
give you a a loss uh back. And then you
can do whatever you want. I would we
would recommend you fit scaling laws um
to these uh
points, and then you extrapolate, and
then we give you a budget, and you're we
basically uh evaluate how well your
model landed.
So, it is meant to I was going to say
it's meant to kind of replicate the
high-stress uh scenarios if you actually
had a budget that like, you know, $100
million that you needed to spend. Um and
you have to be very careful about what
how you uh spend this.
Um of course, this is low low stakes. Um
Okay.
So,
so at this point, um you will have you
trained a model, you know how to make it
fast, you know how to scale up. Um
you know, now what's missing?
You know, what do you train the model
on?
And that's going to be the subject of
the data section, um which is, you know,
arguably one of the most important
things because data quality
is is basically specifies how good your
model is going to be.
Um
One way to also frame it is, you know,
what do you want your model to do?
Right? Data basically is uh reflects
what your model wants. So, do you want
to speak multiple languages, be good at,
you know, having a conversation? Do you
want to do run long agentic coding
tasks?
Um and so, part of that is also going
to, you know, so we're going to start by
talking about evaluation,
which uh basically defines the
capabilities that you like your model to
have.
Um you know, one um thing we'll talk
about is um evaluation is a fairly,
you know, deep topic. Um not just it's
not just about like, you know, running
on some benchmarks.
Um there are internal evaluation metrics
for model development, and what's
matters here is that um
you know, smoothness across uh scales so
that they're, you know, remember we want
things to be predictable. Um relative
performance matters. You don't care
necessarily how well this uh um
you know, does an absolute charge
because, you know, let's say perplexity
number is just like what is a perplexity
1. you know, two um on some, you know,
held-out data really mean?
Um and then there's external metrics.
These are things that you report to
um your
your customers or your reviewers or
whoever you're uh presenting your thing
to. And here ecologically validity
really matters. And I think sometimes
these two things two things get
completed, but I think they really serve
two distinct purposes.
And so, you can think about perplexity
is something that uh is really helpful
for internal development. And still to
this day,
you know, perplexity is is a very good
way of capturing the intrinsic uh
quality of a model without getting kind
of worrying about bench maxing. Now,
there's a separate question of what you
run your um
evals on. Um and the recommended thing
is, well, if you have some data that's
not on the internet, that would be good
because uh you can avoid uh
contamination.
Okay. So, uh if
um and then there's uh advanced use
cases, which are more uh representative
of external-facing
um use cases.
So, one thing to also note is that, you
know, language models are purportedly
very general purpose. Right? So, it's
suitable only fitting that we actually
need a very diverse set of evaluations.
And I would always recommend having many
evaluations that look at you can average
them into a single number, but often
that average conflates a lot of
different um things.
Okay. So, now after we set up the evals,
we know what we're building.
Um
how do you get the data?
Well, first thing is that data does not
just uh fall from the sky.
Um it has to be actively, you know,
curated. Um often, I think um you know,
in you know, especially in in classes
and also in research, sometimes you're
just given a data set, and then it's
like, okay, well, now I do stuff on the
data set. But um a lot of language
models, especially if you want to
collect these large data sets, you have
to go actively uh look at it. So, web
pages are called from the internet. Um
there's books, I guess, which is
controversial at this at this point, but
archive papers, GitHub code, and and so
on. This is an old figure from the the
pile from 2021, and you can see,
you know, language modeling data sets
are fairly uh diverse. Um there's
especially these days, I think, a lot of
uh contention around
is it fair use to train on copyrighted
data? Um
maybe sometimes you have to license
data,
and so on. So, there's legal issues
around data, which um I think are quite
in, you know, important. For example, uh
a lot of GitHub code doesn't have a
license.
So, uh how do you interpret that? Do you
think assume it's permissive, or do you
be conservative and assume it's not
permissive?
Um
So, there's also
uh the fact is that
data is not even text, right? It's
either HTML or PDFs, or code is
directories, and this requires
processing to turn it into actual text
to be usable for training.
So, that's the top uh topic of data
processing.
Uh there's a few steps that has to
happen here. Transformation, converting
some non-text thing into text. Um
uh filtering,
um keeping only the good stuff. Um if
the random internet uh document in
Common Crawl is extremely bad, and you
the
and you don't want to train on it, most
likely. Um you want to deduplicate. Um
there's multiple sources, so how do you
uh combine the different sources?
Um and then finally, more
uh
recently, there's been a lot of uh work
on, you know, generating synthetic data,
which could uh mean taking the real data
and just rewriting it into things that
are more like the downstream task, or or
just some more Wikipedia-like, or
whatever uh the whatever you want. So,
this is an active area of research.
Um also, data can be used both for
pre-training,
uh something called mid-training, which
is usually the high-quality data that
you put at the the end of the
pre-training um step. And this includes
long context uh data, such as, you know,
maybe big uh code repositories or books.
And then finally there's post-training
data, which are
you know, maybe conversations or genetic
traces with you know, tool calling.
So, in assignment four,
we're going to make you start with
a very
raw corpus, like a raw web crawl, and do
all the work to
um
um to filter and to dedupe and make the
data uh clean. So, this is
I would say
I don't know if I would call it not fun,
but it is certainly I think a lot of you
know, what people would call you know,
dirty work, but that is I think part of
an important part of building a language
model from scratch. So, you have to get
the full experience.
Okay. So, finally
um alignment
um so far we've basically trained a
model using full supervision. Predict
the next token or the next few tokens.
Um now, at this point the model should
already be reasonable.
Um
but we can improve it further
by using weak supervision. And why weak
supervision? It's because
um sometimes it's easier to critique
than it is to generate. So, you can't
always have data that says this is the
right response to this prompt, but maybe
you can have a way of specifying what
good looks like.
So, then the basic template is that you
generate responses from a model, you
score them either with a human or verify
or LM judge, and then you update the
model to prefer better responses. This
can be instantiated either through
various RL algorithms such as PPO or
GRPO, or in a simpler for preference
data DPO.
Um
So, the challenges around RL
are that
RL algorithms are unstable and
uh you know, hard to tune. Some of you
probably know this from first-hand you
know, experience.
Personally, I prefer to keep things as
much in the full truly supervised case
as long as possible, and then finally
okay, fine, I have to do RL.
Um but you know, some people for
whatever reason like doing RL.
Um
Also, what we'll hopefully talk about
this year is that if you do RL at scale
and try to maximize your throughput,
there's a actually a lot of systems
challenges.
Um you have to have an inference server
and a training server, and then the
inference server um has to generate
these rollouts, especially if you do RL
against environments that involve code
execution. It's a whole kind of
orchestration game. And then if your
workers
lag behind or then you get into
off-policy issues, and then you're
constantly kind of juggling
um this
on-policyness with a desire to kind of
maximize throughput. It's it's a big
wonderful mess, which hopefully we'll um
talk more about when we come to that.
So,
um assignment five,
um we're still
uh deciding what exactly we want to do.
Last year it was implement DPO and GRPO
and get it working for some
um you know, math benchmark, but um
we'll see how how much farther we can
push it on the realistic dimension this
year.
Okay. So, again, remember it's about
efficiency,
um and efficiency can mean
uh either data efficiency or compute
efficiency. So, the way to think about
it, you have all these resources. You
have data, you have the hardware, which
has compute uh cores, you have memory,
communication bandwidth, and you're just
trying to figure out how do you build
the best model according to some
evaluation
um given a fixed set of resources.
So, you can through this lens, I think
you can actually think about a lot of
these uh design decisions as um
optimizing for this. So, systems,
clearly that's about um compute
efficiency.
Um tokenization, as I mentioned before,
um it's you know, you can't just work
with raw bytes, but that's going to be
very compute inefficient, and um
at least with today's model
architectures. And so, a lot of
tokenization is about improving compute
efficiency. Model architecture, many of
the changes that we'll see um
are motivated by reducing the memory or
flops.
Um in fact, a lot of them are influenced
by the need to have faster inference.
Um
data filtering, you can also view as uh
through efficiency lens. We don't want
to waste time updating gradients on a
bunch of redundant uh bad data, even if
it might not hurt you, but it hurts you
in the sense that if you have a fixed
compute budget, more time on bad data
means less time on good data.
And then finally, scaling laws is
explicitly about how you can essentially
do effective hyperparameter tuning on
much smaller models.
And now, tomorrow we might become data
constrained in the calculus
uh of what design decisions you should
take might change, but I think the
overall mindset, which we're trying to
teach you, is you know, think about the
efficiency of your approach.
Okay.
Um let me stop there. Are there any
questions about any of these uh
assignments or uh topics?
Okay.
So, now let's uh do uh tokenization. So,
this is we're jumping into our first uh
unit here.
Um
So, Andrej Karpathy has this really good
video on tokenization. You should check
it out. Um
So,
let's starting point is raw text is what
is text. It's Unicode strings.
Um
and on the other hand, the language
model places a distribution over
sequences of tokens, usually represented
as indices. So, we need a procedure that
encodes these strings into tokens, and
also a procedure that decodes tokens
back into strings. So, a tokenizer is
basically something that can do this
round trip.
So, here are some examples to give you a
flavor um for how tokenizers work.
Actually, I should have tried to get
internet earlier, so this is not going
to work. Okay, if you go to the site,
you can play around with different
tokenizers. Um
So, some observations here.
Um
there's and you'll you'll appreciate why
tokenizers are kind of annoying, why
people want to get rid of them.
So, a word and its uh
and a word with conglomerate with its
preceding space um are different you
know, tokens.
Um so, many of tokens you'll actually
see are space word, which is you know,
fine, but kind of strange. Um So, this
hello and this uh hello is actually two
completely different indices that have
nothing to do with each other.
So, um
and sometimes, depending on the
tokenizer you use, numbers are
represented with um
this
every few digits is a token. Sometimes
it's predictable, and sometimes it's
it's not. Some tokenizers try to make
every digit a token, but then you're
blowing up the number of tokens you
have, so there's some trade-off there.
Um
So, here's the
um GPT-5 tokenizer.
Uh so,
uh it can take the string and
uh convert it into
you know, these indices.
Um
and then you can uh decode it back into
the string. And a
tokenizer should round trip. If you
implement a tokenizer that doesn't round
trip, you have a problem.
Um
So, the the compression ratio
here is the number of bytes per token.
So, in this case,
um we have the number of bytes is of
this string is 20. The number of tokens
is eight, and you do 20 / 8, so the
compression ratio is 2.5.
Okay, so 2.5 bytes per token. The larger
the compression ratio, that means the
shorter the sentence, which is good
because attention is quadratic, and you
want to make sure the sent sequence is
shorter.
Um
Now, you could obviously increase the
compression ratio by increasing the
vocab size,
um but then you get into sparsity, where
more and more um because every element
of vocab is treated as like a as a
distinct element.
Um so, these days uh tokenizers, um
especially multilingual tokenizers, have
you know, 100k or 200k um you know,
tokens.
Distinct tokens.
Um so, uh you can look at the GPT token
vocabulary. I think we'll skip it this
in the interest of time.
Okay, so how do you build a tokenizer?
So, I'm going to go through this fast,
but um
So, the first thing you might do is
like, well, Unicode string, that's a
sequence already of Unicode characters,
and each character is an integer, which
you can call ORD in Python, and you get
some number out.
And this can be converted into
characters, so let's just build a
character-level tokenizer, which
basically breaks up each character and
encodes it in a token, and then this can
decode back. Like this is good.
So, now, there are 150k
uh Unicode characters, so your vocab
size could be 150k,
um which is
which is you know, a lot I I mean, it's
not crazy,
but um I think the bigger problem is
that many characters are actually rare.
Um which means that it's really an
inefficient use of a vocabulary.
And and also the compression ratio, um
which kind of reflects this is not that
great. So, most of the time you're
actually using, um,
a lot of tokens to represent your your
sequence and many of the the the the
indices,
um,
are actually not being very used. So,
this is like not a very good tokenizer.
Um, so here's another attempt.
So, you can turn strings into bytes.
So, Unicode has a UTF-8 encoding, which
means that
um,
you can sometimes, uh, a string like A
is just one byte and sometimes a string
is, uh, you know, multiple bytes. So,
let's build a tokenizer around that.
So, um, we can take this string and
convert it into a sequence of bytes and
notice that this is a longer sequence
now and but all of the
all the numbers are between 0 and 255
because that's what a byte means.
Um, and the compression ratio is, uh,
is one, which is, uh, which is not
great. Right? So, byte sequences are can
be very long, um, but the vocab size is,
uh, small.
Okay, so
now, okay, so the both of these are like
really bad. So, here's let's try to make
some progress. So, this is what actually
people used to do in NLP, um, if, uh,
people remember. So, if you take a
string, I can just chunk it up into, uh,
break it up by spaces or some regular
expression, um,
and let's just call each of these
chunks,
uh, a token.
Okay, so what is good about this one is
that each token is meaningful
because humans invented words and words
tend to have a stable semantic meaning,
um, so in there but your vocab size is
the number of distinct chunks in the
training data, which could be all a lot.
And also your, uh, compression ratio, I
mean, it's it's it's quite, you know,
good but the vocabulary can be huge.
Actually, it's worse than that because,
um,
the, uh, the vocabulary could be
actually unbounded, right? Because at
test time you might get some sequence
and you tokenize and then you have a
token you've never seen before and
people used to
assign these like unk token but that's
like really ugly and can mess up your
perplexity uh, calculations.
So,
um, this is also not not great.
Okay, so what we're actually going to do
is called byte pair encoding.
And this was introduced a long time ago
for data compression way before language
models, um,
uh, were really
on the scene, really.
Uh, it was first introduced to NLP for
doing neural machine translation,
um, and
the first, uh, paper that,
uh, used BPE
to, uh, for LMs was, uh, GPT-2.
So, the basic idea is you're going to
train the tokenizer on raw text to
construct a vocabulary that's tailored
to the data.
And you're also going to have this
property that everything becomes can be
tokenized if it's rare, then it just
breaks up into smaller units rather than
having this unk token.
Um, so
so common sequences can be, um, are
going to be represented as one token,
rare sequences are going to be split
into multiple tokens. That's the idea.
Okay, so the algorithm is fairly, uh,
simple conceptually.
So, you start basically with your your
corpus, let's assume it's one long
sequence.
Um, you get a byte sequence, each byte
starts as a token and then we're going
to merge,
um, successive pairs of adjacent tokens
that are occurred the most frequently.
Okay, so let's step through how this is
going to work in code. So, here's a
simple string, the cat in the hat,
and, uh, here's the implementation of
the BPE algorithm.
Um, so we're going to,
uh, turn that into a sequence of bytes,
um, and then we're going to
um,
first, we're going to basically count
the number of times successive tokens
appear. So, 116 104 shows up twice.
Um, so we get this
and then we're going to find the
um, the pair that uh,
happens most number of times. So, that's
116 104. I guess there's a few ties but
we'll just take the first one.
And then we're going to merge that pair.
And by merging that pair, what we do is
we create a new token.
In this case,
um, this is going to be called token
256. It's going to represent this pair
and we're going to add it to our
vocabulary. So, 256 is going to
represent the sequence th. So, t and h
have been merged and we're going to call
every time we see th, that's going to
we're going to use 256 to represent
that.
And then we go through indices and then
we replace every occurrence of 116 104
with 256. So, those two places have been
replaced.
And then we iterate. So, the next time,
uh, we do this, we're going to find 256
and 101, we're going to merge that and
now we have 257
and then, uh, we're going to merge that,
um, one more time and we're going to get
258. So, over time, the sequence is, uh,
shrinking,
um, and the vocabulary size is growing.
Okay, so,
um,
let me
and the compression ratio,
uh,
here is that we get for this, I mean,
this toy example is 1.5. Um,
okay, so now that you have a tokenizer,
um, how do you tokenize new text? Well,
um, you take a new string and you encode
it and conceptually what happens is
that, um, you basically go through the
set of merges, uh, that you've made and
then you just apply,
uh, the merges to your your string.
Okay, let me not actually not step
through that code.
Um, so that will give you a sequence.
Um, so this is the sequence, uh,
encoding of the quick brown fox and
then, uh, when you decode it, you get
the same thing, you know, back.
So, um,
I went to through this a bit fast just
in the interest of time. Um,
I will say that this,
uh, implementation
works. This is a full-blown BPE
implementation. It's extremely slow.
So, in assignment one,
we're going to ask you to, um, basically
make it faster.
Um, so currently encode, uh, loops over
all the, you know, merges, which is very
slow because you might have the number
of merges you have is essentially
essentially, um, the vocab size minus,
you know, 256.
Um, so you only want to loop over the
merges that that matter. Um,
and you have to build some indices to
make that, you know, happen.
Um, there's some, you know, details
around special tokens. Conceptually not
deep but important to building a modern
tokenizer. Um, another thing is that
I've presented the tokenizer just for
simplicity as you take an entire string
and then you try to tokenize it. Really,
what happens is that you break it up
into, uh,
your text into chunks and then you apply
tokenizer on each, uh, chunk. So, that's
going to be much faster.
Um, and then,
you know, and then try to make it as
fast as possible. Um, at some point you
might realize that Python is just not
very fast and if you want to implement
it in, you know, say your favorite
language,
uh, Rust or C or something, then go for
it.
Okay, so quick summary. Tokenizers
convert between strings and tokens or
indices.
Um, the previous character-based,
byte-based, word-based are uh, highly
suboptimal in this, uh, in their own
way.
BPE is is, um, effective heuristics that
is data-driven so, uh,
um, it seems to be
uh, pretty effective. Now, like I said
before, uh, maybe next year I don't have
to teach this but, uh, for this year
we're stuck with tokenization.
Um,
you know, even if we get rid of
tokenization though, um, I think
whatever solution replaces it, I think
has to satisfy the following properties,
right? If you have the model, the
transformer needs to operate on some
sort of abstractions of the sequence.
And this is most evident if you think
about, you know, um, not just text but
video or or DNA, um, sequences where,
um,
you know, the individual,
um, bytes or units are actually
quite kind of low signal to noise, um,
and you have to do some sort of
abstraction to lift it into a place
where you can do modeling on that.
Um, and then finally, as I mentioned,
um, chunks should be kind of variable.
You want adaptive computation. Um, not
all,
you know, bytes are treated the same and
if you don't do that, I think you're
going to be suboptimal. So, if any
end-to-end solution also, I think has to
have these properties.
Okay, so with that, I will end. Next
time on Wednesday, we're going to start
the unit on resource accounting, so
which is sort of a,
you know, a baby systems, I would say.
And then after that, we're going to go
back into architectures and, uh, go from
there.
All right.